[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right everyone welcome to the stoa
i'm peter limberg the steward of the
stoa
this though is a place for us to go here
and dialogue about what matters most
the nice edge of this very moment we've
got some mental models
to discuss at the nice edge so today if
you haven't been here before
this is part of a sense maker in
residence series
this happens over a course of a month
four sessions same time
uh same day um where a person comes
who's making sense of the world uh helps
us make sense of the world and we can
make sense of it together
um and peter wayne is here uh
entrepreneur uh student of the human
condition
uh is going to talk about the mental
models he uses to navigate the
complexities of our world
and last session was really fun he had a
powerpoint listed all his models
and today he has a set of mental models
that um
he's going to talk about so how today is
going to work if you have any questions
uh anytime peter is talking follow them
in the chat
uh have like a cue or question before
your actual question
this will go on youtube so if you want
me to read on your behalf and you don't
want to be on youtube
just let me know uh and then when we're
at that point where we're going to feel
questions
i'll take you in you'll mute yourself
ask your question to peter
we'll be here for an hour um we'll kind
of feel it if we can be here a little
bit uh
over the hour but i think that's that
that being said
i will take peter in give him host
access so he can share a screen so
good morning my friend good morning
thank you for having me back uh hold on
let me change my
ikea background here to uh something a
little more reasonable
something nice for the morning feels
comfortable looking at the nice ikea
furniture you got going
it is in fact exactly designed to make
you feel comfortable and that is
relevant let me make you feel
uncomfortable without a fighter jet in
your face no that's not good
um let's do this just something nice and
miyazaki so
yes um okay let me go ahead and show you
i also
i do have a powerpoint again today just
to kind of walk through some stuff i
don't
i don't know if that's is that typical
or
um i don't know i'm uh
50 50 uh i quite enjoyed the powerpoint
okay good so let's see here share
screen and
there it is
um okay so let me go ahead and to
actually maybe i'll just do it this way
we can sort of well no i'll just go into
presenter mode
okay so um thank you everyone for for
joining today
and uh sharing sharing your time and
part of your day with me um
the the today i decided what i would
talk about um
is the idea well i've lost my mouse now
so somehow zoom
has decided that i don't have a mouse
okay there it is it's good enough okay
so today
i want to talk about relationships and
um the sense of self
and that touches on identity it touches
on a bunch of different interesting
things
um it's kind of a shift from what we
talked about
last time last time was much more you
know metaphysical and kind of a very
cerebral exercise about
how we how we look at what is a thing
and what is reality
this is also talking about reality but
it's talking much more than about the
subjective aspects of reality
um let me zoom in just a little bit all
right
so um so let's get right into it so um
i think typically when we think about
relationships um
we think about them as okay this
connective thing between
cells or between individuals or between
an object and another object we can talk
about the relationship that
um we have with each other we can talk
about the relationships between people
the relationship between a car and the
road
or a spacecraft and the gravitational
field around it
you know we talk about relationships as
between two things between two objects
um and you can draw it very simply like
this as sort of
what we call a node link diagram so you
have nodes and the relationships are the
links between them
but when we construct it in this way the
emphasis
is entirely it's almost it's almost hard
to see it
until you look at it um but there is
this extreme prejudice towards
the self the atomic selves and objects
as being primary they're the primary
things they're the nodes i mean even in
the
we don't call it a link of nodes we call
it node link diagram
right even our emphasis in the word
order really shows you
the the perspective we have on this
which is that there are these nodes
and we can if we're talking about
physics or we're talking about
psychology we can talk about the selves
or the nodes as atomic things under
themselves
um and and then we can talk about the
relationship to other things the
relationship is secondary right
and so i would like when i talk about
inverting this view
um what i mean is what if we view the
relationships as the first class
thing what if it's actually it's not
atoms
and then there's some interaction
between atoms but the interaction
the field is the primary thing
okay now does that make sense like like
it's a different kind of view i think
i'm
obviously just having seen some peter's
writing uh i know peter understands
this um concept right this idea that if
we actually flip this around
and we don't view the atomized
individuals we don't view
the the car as an object on the road
we don't just view a planet in the space
of the gravitational field we flip
around we talk about the gravitational
field as the primary thing
that through its action pushes and
smooshes a bunch of things together to
form planets
all of a sudden i mean it's the same
physics it's the same stuff and yet
it completely flips the world on its
head
if you view yourself not as an agent and
a self that has relationships
but rather you are the emergent result
of all of the relationships
around you it's kind of like it's it's
kind
it's kind of interesting right and a
relationship is just a tube right in
this way it's a tube
with inputs and outputs at either end
right it's a binding
between two different things or
if you have a whole lot of them it's a
field it's like the ocean it's a thing
that
it's a binding energy that creates
atomized
locations and so if you then um take
this
you can sort of see the self as the
region
as defined by relationships so if you
are a baby
and imagine i don't know how many people
here have have children i know there's
some um
there's a there's a wide variety of uh
age groups represented here
at the stoa but as i was raising my
child i began to realize
well i have two children a 10 year old
and a six-year-old now but i began to
realize
how much my language and my interaction
with them
was explicitly creating a relationship
that defined selfhood for them
um and in fact if you look at childhood
like early childhood psychology and you
look at some of these kinds of things
you can define that like the pij uh
scale of of um
of infant development there's there's a
there's an early stage where they're
just a blob of like neurons of meat
right and then eventually the neurons
get a sense of like
oh there's persistence of there's a
constant concept of object persistence
like oh when a thing moves behind
another thing
it's still the same thing so their brain
and their visual cortex
cortexes are sort of still wiring up
this basic level
at a perceptual level and over time they
develop a theory of action i can move my
hands i can suck on my thumb
i can cry and i get milk right there's
all these things
but as they become um as they really
develop a sense of of coherent self
the parents around them are the ones
that then define the social self and
begin to give them a sense of
i am your caregiver i or i am your
punisher or i define what you can do
and and there's like this so even from a
very early age
as humans we're molded by our
interactions with the the caregivers
around us
and as we go into late a childhood into
teenage year
time frame that's when we start to
develop
an inner or innate self you can think of
this as the id
right and then projecting the ego and
that's back pressure against the social
cells coming in
and of course this comes to a head in
our teenage years as we as we exceed
and break and push back on some of these
relationships some of which have been
fundamental to us since we were
you know blobs of neurons and meat right
and so
this idea that that selfhood is not an
atomic like it ends at my skin
okay myself certainly forces out into my
skin it's locally projected into a
microphone which then goes out into the
internet to all of you all
so myself is actually quite extended in
the age of the internet but
even if i were to think of myself as
just this physical body defined by skin
that's that's a very very uh
impoverished view
because i'm a social human being in the
modern world myself
my identity my avatar is actually uh
the the end points of a lot of these
relations a lot of these um
these relationships and even here uh
before peter invited me here onto the
stoa
i did not exist inside this social realm
now i do exist in the social realm
as a person as a sense maker but as a
person who's been given the privilege of
the platform to speak to all of you
right
and so all of so many aspects and i've
gained that now
part of my identity so all of these
different aspects of selfhood are
actually defined by the relationships
that we allow to come in or that we
invest into it's an input output
right if i do a terrible job at this
right now if i completely just waste
everyone's time and i'm quite boring
and i add no value whatsoever you know i
probably won't be invited back right
and so there's there's an input and
output there's expectations and there's
stress
stress is just the shifting of that
boundary of self
with it not not just but in the sense of
social stress we can talk about that
as the the the the energy it takes to
kind of shift
um the the boundaries of stuff within
all of these the social environment we
live in
so that's that's sort of the the the the
way i wanted to
kick this off was to invert the view of
relationships from being just
a connective thing that atoms do to
actually being
the field that actually makes atoms
possible that defines what the shape of
the atom is
so and this is um full disclosure
i i have a little like nerd out part of
me that
likes to look at chemistry and atomic
physics and to think about atoms
themselves in this way
that actually the cartesian newtonian to
bohr and rutherfordian model
of what we think of as an atom is um
it's quite literal it's like oh here's
the planet you know the center of the
nucleus of the atom electrons orbiting
it
except we know that it's not really
electrons orbiting it's a quantum
you know electric uh quantum
probability wave function that defines
what we're likely to find electrons
but if you start going to that more more
you realize wait it's just a giant
entangled quantum
probability field and is there even
electron unless we make a measurement on
it
if we make a measure of a certain form
our measuring device gets entangled into
the field and so what the f
is an atom is an electron is any of the
stuff so
it's really interesting this blend
between field to corpuscular or atomic
theories
even in physics hard hard physics and
i'm i
i'm not a practicing physicist anymore
but i did train as a physicist in
college
so what i'm telling you for those who
don't know physics there's nothing i'm
not
getting all mumbo jumbo like quantum
mysticism on you that's literally
actually the way that quantum physicists
think about this
they know that we don't actually have a
hard model of like here's exactly where
the object is here's exactly where the
electron is
we talk about as a mathematical wave
function that is the most proper way to
talk about that's how we make lasers and
everything else
is because we think in those terms so
even in physics
where we're where we most successfully
use the word atom and atomization
when it gets down to it the mechanics of
interaction we have to use
wave theories and so here i'm suggesting
that when we think about the relational
dynamics between people in a social
environment and
being humans which are not just you know
a proton or a neutron or whatever
that we can use a similar concept rather
than seeing ourselves as atomic
individuals
see ourselves as zones of identity uh
zones of identity that
um have pressure back pressure against
all of these different social
relationships coming into us and one
thing i'll say about this that's very
interesting is if you view this in the
context
uh uh well i'll talk about this later in
the q a remind me to talk about
celebrity and fame culture
okay if i forget but this directly
touches on
that idea of brands and celebrity and
fame culture
so anyway um so that's that's a
different way of looking at
relationships but if we ask okay how are
relationships formed
if they're primal where do they come
from and
and this touches on then
inter-subjective reality it touches on
because a relationship you know we can
say we want to be primal
but it does seem to have like things
there need to be things relating to each
other to form a relationship don't
doesn't there so um so there's a great
uh document written by a guy named joe
edelman uh back in 2017
about conviviality and human
relationships and um
just i mean really really fantastic um
and it's actually google doc i don't
know if you'll be able to find it if you
search for it but i did link it here in
this and i will upload
i don't promise to upload the previous
presentation haven't yet i will upload
these presentations so you guys can
view the links but um but joe did this
really wonderful analysis and he
did a lot of study on this stuff and he
looked at like
this question of where does our sense of
togetherness he was talking about this
not as just a
diatic relationship between two
individuals but just in general
the social environment where does our
sense of togetherness come from
and i thought this was a nice little
chart to look at uh demographic affinity
or we could look at you know different
kinds of um
labor relationships and then um what he
called simultaneous feeling down there
and he and he evolved from this
to um uh that evolves but he in that
same document
he has this which then kind of narrows
into kind of
that dyadic mode between two individuals
uh or you have two
two agents that do not have a
relationship how does a relationship
form
um and and he is ultimately identified
relationships requiring shared values to
exist and and i talk about his trust
right so what is the origins of trust in
human relationships
these are really the building blocks
shared values and and building trust
and he talked about four different ways
that we discover values
and i have this is one of my mental
models that i love the most um he has a
if you look for joe edelman uh for
social worlds
he's got this brilliant write-up about
that as well that that talks about
at the end of the day what how do we
actually start to relate to people
and he identifies these four modes we
can have mutual appreciation
so together we both go look at a piece
of art or together we both watch a tv
show
or we mutually we go both go and pet the
same dog you know it could be
something there builds relationship
because there's mutual
appreciation now we can also just talk
to each other just talking is
but talking does not mean using language
as weapons talking is actually talking
um so so you can that's another way to
kind of build more trust
conflicts is another way to build trust
so i i tend to call trustful conflict
i'm
talking about this at the corporate
management level but
some people like to think that oh we
want a safe space and we
everyone trusts each other means no
one's getting hurt and it's like no
no no that just means everyone's
pretending to trust each other
actual trustful relationships are ones
in which you can disagree and you know
the other person
won't come at you in a different angle
so going back to that
to the the previous slide here
um trust means that people know how to
stay in their lane
and they're not they're going to stop at
the boundary where you want them to stop
before it comes into damaging your inner
your inner self
they respect your boundaries that you're
setting that's what trust means in that
sense
but conflict simply means we're working
through a problem together and
if we go and solve a problem together in
a sense that's also kind of a flavor of
mutual appreciation right these all kind
of build on each other
but trustall conflict is such a hugely
important part
of building uh shared values uh and
emerging a relationship because you're
both
it's sort of instead of two people
looking inwards at each other they're
facing outwards right they're facing
outwards towards a shared problem they
have a shared mission
shared values and lastly exploring
together
and this is very important too because
when we explore truly explore
where we're in a liminal we're operating
in a liminal zone we don't know
we're not there to confirm a hypothesis
we have to prove ourselves right to all
the people around us
we are exploring because we literally
don't know let's just go and talk about
it
and it's in a sense it's also so the
left you can think of as um
somewhat inward facing towards each
other in the dyad and the last two
are sort of outward facing you're either
facing something that threatens you so
you're you're resolving a conflict maybe
it's an internal conflict maybe it's
external conflict
exploring is definitely outwards facing
right you're you're looking at some new
space together
so these are ways that we build values
that's how that's how essentially
if you think about this back to the wave
and field analogy
when two things if you have if you throw
a rock
if you or maybe the best thing about it
is like if you have um
if you have the surface of a pond and
you throw a rock into here and you throw
a rock over there
those waves will just randomly like you
know pass through each other
but if you throw rocks of roughly the
similar size
in at the same speed those waves will
form a resonance pattern
and they will form fixed points of of um
of uh constructive and destructive
interference
and those wave patterns will be in
resonance so this is really about
creating resonant values in that in that
field in that relationship field
now that's just diaz again we think
about relationship as me to you
um but if you think about just four if
you have just four people
or four agents or four nodes how many
relationships are there
if you think only in terms of dyadic
you've got seven pairwise
relationships binary or diatonic
relationships
but if you think about a relationship as
being one person
towards a dyad then there's 12 of those
actually and if you look at as one
person to uh a three-way group there's
four of those i mean i'm not going to
read this chart but
but the when you get to the 2 2 and the
4-0 is very interesting
the idea that relationships themselves
have relationships
and this is all very abstract and
mathematical but to make this extremely
concrete for people
think about a family with a mother
father and a son and a daughter this is
my family right so so me and my wife and
my son and daughter
we can identify all of these different
relationships within that
the relationship we need to talk about
this intuitively what is the
relationship
any of us can look at a family and say
what's the relationship here between the
parents and the kids
that's now a pair to a pair that is a
two-two relationship
right what is so so you say well this
family wow
it's it's got real issues because the
father is like uh
alcoholic he's an addict of some sort um
and so the the this has a there's a
broken father figure in this
relationship
that's a one well you can see that's a
one two right that father is a bad
father figure to the
to the kids but the father is also a bad
husband to the wife that's a one one
right and that father is also a bad
father in the family that's a one
three so even in a simple
like you know your kind of core 1950s
uh sitcom level family unit
you've got you just add these up how
many different relationships let's see
here that's 10 22
26 27 relationships
among four people and this is what you
get to when you stop thinking in terms
of just
nodes because if you think just in terms
of nodes you would say well there's
seven binary there's seven relationships
because you count the lines there's
seven
uh seven of them right or i guess in
here there's six before they get to
seven
one two three four five six
maybe miscounted it's quite embarrassing
because it's going to go on youtube
one or three i kind of swore i counted
somehow
maybe i'm missing one somewhere maybe
it's only six whatever the point is
there's very few
but when you start looking at
assemblages when you look at
relationships themselves
as being things you can have a
relationship with it becomes much much
larger
and with this last one may seem like a
nullity right to say well
if we talk about a four-way uh you know
a
a uh it's not a tertiary quaternary
thing what do they relate to there's no
there's nothing for them related to well
they might relate to other external
things it's like our family
and if you read any jane austen it's
like how does our family sit in the
social context you know relative to
netherfield and all these things
right there's a very good sense that
yeah that multi-way relationship that's
a thing
that's actually a unit that four-way
relationship
um that has a reality to it and when you
talk about
that you know there's a there's a in law
you can sue i think there's um
you can basically file a civil lawsuit
if someone
um it's a concept of loss of consortium
so if you have a couple and then a third
party interferes
like you know by seducing one of the
couple
then the other can sue that person for
loss of consortium
as in having destroyed the relationship
right and we even in popular culture in
the vernacular
we talk about you know some like woman
that goes to only date married men
as a home wrecker right not a husband
predator but as a home wrecker
so even in these kinds of terms we
recognize that the multi-way
relationship that concept of home
is just sort of you know any any number
of people living within that family unit
that family relationship
so again this is a very long exposition
on a single slide where i might have
made a math mistake
but the point is that this is this is a
very fundamentally different way to look
at the
world stop viewing people as atoms
start viewing them as just a collection
of relationship endpoints
and ask about the relationships they're
in and also don't view relationships as
just being this pipe even though i
showed a tube earlier
they are actually fields they are kind
of collections of waves resonating with
each other they're
they're networks and webs and they have
a reality to them
well in the open source world right
something very close to my to my work
and near and dear to my heart
when we talk about a project forking
what's changing there is not someone
made a copy of the source code and
changed five lines
it's actually that the relationship of
the developers in the developer
community
is sundering and the people in it are
saying we're okay with sundering with
you
we're splitting like mitosis we're going
to split now
and there's something there's a feeling
of loss well what is that feeling of
loss what has been lost it's all the
same people
you got twice as much code what's been
lost what's been lost
is that the relationship of n
that that sort of you know whatever you
want to call this order
n size relationship web and complex has
now been reduced to two times
n over two complexes which are not the
same right this is metcalfe's law
in a nutshell uh metcalf is the um guy
who invented ethernet
which is kind of how whenever you plug
in a jack you know into the wall for
your computer
uh the protocol speaks nowadays it's all
ethernet he invented that and he had a
law a network
a law about networks it's from netcap's
law which is that the value of a network
grows as n squared right where n is the
number of nodes in the network
um this is why facebook has astronomical
valuations why all the social media
companies
the investors encouraging them to build
viral loops into their thing to get more
people
because the value goes n squared this is
also why extractive capitalism loves
this dynamic because
extractive capitalism looks for uh
exponentials
and a quadratic uh well i mean sorry
n squared um a quadratic approximates an
exponential
in small parts if you kind of look
pretty close to the
depending on the the coefficient so in
any case this thing
is something that i encourage this is
the mental model that i use all the time
where people talk about this that their
their relationship was broken whatever
i stopped looking at them as people i
look at what was
tell me about the relationship what was
important about the relationship itself
what is the relationship
what power did it have unto itself
beyond what just
these individuals can do every firm
every institution everything that we
live in
nowadays the 95 percent of the world
that is construct beyond the physical
all of those things are just swimming in
this stuff
it's all relationships your relationship
to the institution the relation within
institution the relationships of
organizations to each other
it's all actually much better understood
not as individuals not as people but as
relationships
and how those individuals might be able
to impact those relationships but the
relationships are sort of like the
the big bag of the bagpipe that's got
all the air in it you know the
individual might blow into a little bit
but that bag of air that's the
relationship that's going to power all
of the sound
so this is one of my mental models
now related to this i'll take a
small pause to have some coffee because
i'm talking slower slower now
[Music]
related to this concept is dunbar's
number
and dunbar um is this is a actually a
fairly recent concept uh
as far as you know academic sort of
models and whatnot it only emerged in
the 90s
um and it's
everyone who mentions dumbar it's one of
those things or everyone who mentions it
mentions it with a critical eye like
well if you believe it or we know it's
an approximation or it's a convenient
uh it's one of those things that went
what do they talk about uh
gosh johnny nelson talked about this
hilariously it's like one of those
things that went from academia
to the talk circuit to the cocktails
cocktail circuit right
so it's a thing that people you know
talk about now without um
without really leaving diving deep to
like well what's the basis of it is it
real
but the idea is very simple it's just
that based on the neocortex size of
humans and based on what we've seen
in anthropological studies um
it looks like the natural size for
uh human kind of primeval sort of
uh natural cohesion social cohesion is
around 150 somewhere between 100 to 250
but about 150.
and it's really the idea is that you can
keep social contact and send social
intimacy
with about that many people beyond that
you kind of lose track
right and we have this kind of um
this kind of limit is not new so like in
uh plato
right right like sort of said maybe 3000
people was as big as you would get
for some kind of an integrated republic
um
beyond which then you sort of just see
all of it as the other you don't see it
as us
the limit of us is somewhere depending
on what you're trying to do
between 150 to 3 000 i guess right and
if you are entrepreneurs or you've done
startups or businesses
you know there are distinct phases or
distinct
um limits beyond which the socialization
structure of the group the crew the
click
has to change in order to scale the
mission
so you know between three to five people
you got a thing
you get to about 10 to 15 people then
you have to be a little more explicit
about
how you coordinate when you get to about
30 to 40 there's another little minor
break point but 60 is a really like make
or break thing when you get to 60
on the other side of 60 people 60 to 70
people depending again on the people and
what you're doing you need to then build
explicit meeting structures who knows
what you'd actually
model the communications within as an
explicit first class
thing um and that's exactly a
manifestation of this principle
that you can no longer hold in your head
how other people are relating to each
other what they know who told who what
how people feel about it it just gets
too much you have to create a mailing
list and say well i informed the mailing
list and so now i've done the thing i
need to do
and then how people relate to that
manual list that channel that's on them
right you create institutions you create
processes
so that people then are not relating to
each other they're relating to a pattern
of interaction
and now that's what an institution is
now the nice thing the interesting thing
about this is that dunbar's number is
about human socialization based on
neocortical sort of stuff and
anthropological studies of like
you know people on the banks of some
river and stroth huts right
uh john johnny nelson just recently
published this
great work um where he revisits this in
the context of
the um uh
the the cybernetic era or the the the
you know very online era
and um and he says that you know
dunbar's number is not so much about the
number of people
uh and how many people you have it's not
linear in that
it's about inter relationship
comprehension
how does how do you how does each person
or how does each relationship
interact with all the other
relationships
and he says it's quadratic in the upper
bounds on the relationships
not linear in terms of nodes it's sort
of mathematical but
but it's he's saying it's dunbar's
number is more about
the capacity of the if you go back to
the pond and the waves in the pond
it's not about how many pebbles can you
drop into a pond it's about
how much turbulence can you have on a
pawn surface before it becomes
incomprehensible
to the people to a node within it to a
frog you know on a lily
on a lily frond like trying to you know
a lily pad sorry trying to um
make sense of all the waves coming in
and maybe that's actually not bad
because a lily pad actually does have an
integration surface area over
over the the surface of the pond i like
that so if your frogs on a lily pad
you know all these waves are coming in
if there's a couple of pebbles dropping
in and maybe dunbar
and a neolithic era when the water was a
certain density
150 pebbles coming in was about how much
your lily pad could integrate
instead the frog it still makes sense
with what's going on
in the social media era we need to look
at not just how many
because there's a lot of different rocks
but it's the rate at which the rocks are
breaking that surface of the water
before the frog decides to bail and just
give up and bounce off that lily pad
because it's too chaotic and crazy so so
to make this concrete he says okay look
in classical and classical dumbar
um the idea is that the reason why you
have a limit is because over time
your model of other people and their
relationships to each other
right because again remember
intersubjective belief
is your belief about other people's
beliefs
right subjectivity is your belief inter
subjectivity is your belief about others
beliefs
so this ties directly to this idea of
you relating to a relationship
what do i believe about how my mom feels
about my brother right
what do i believe about how my sister
feels about her boyfriend right
your ability to track all these beliefs
it's an it's intersubjective limit but
the point is that in classic dunbar in
classic you know neolithic whatever kind
of
tribal sort of stuff your model accuracy
grows over time as you have more more
direct interaction
someone who's more distant from you kind
of further out your model accuracy is
not very good
and and it it's you know he drew kind of
this logistic curve whatever maybe it's
linear doesn't really matter
the point is that the more time you
spend with somebody the better you know
and maybe the less time you spend at
some point it's not even worth
you're still stranger to them but if you
form clicks
if people actually cohere together like
if that family
always does stuff together they're that
annoying family that always does
everything together it has happy family
photos on instagram um you can model
them as a click or it's like the cool
kids or the goths or the whoever you
know
the science nerds you could you don't
have to you actually have much greater
model accuracy if you model them as a
click
because you have modeled that
relationship
as almost as a compression right to say
oh well they're science nerds of course
they love bill nye of course they're
going to go and watch
some like rocket launch nonsense or the
lunar eclipse or something right
you can model them very accurately
without having to model individuals
because you've modeled their
relationship to each other as a click
and so so that he calls this model
quality boosting and clicks
so if you have to model each of the ten
goths uh
individually that's hard but if you get
to model all of them is just well that's
the goths they're gonna go to this
concert they're gonna hang out over here
right
you can do it that way and so you can
manage many many more relationships okay
now take this to
the twitter scale global village
and well i'll let you read the text here
geographical coincidence no longer
limits a set of potential relationships
and he quotes a lot of mcluhan
in this in this blog post um where he
talks about
yeah mcluhan saw this the global village
there is no sense of distance
all here is here everyone is here and it
leads to and and again mcluhan called
this
he said this would lead to maximal
disagreement right this is where
zuckerberg's
um arrogance and his naivete becomes
beyond the point of uh like naivety
into explicit negligent harm is that
people knew we know if you go and give a
bunch of people over here a bunch of
people over here
a lot of connection to each other
they're going to kill each other because
they they really
they don't mix you can't mix everyone
together
so the idea here in the twitter scale
global village is that
we can look at the relationships and the
quadratic bound on relationships and
actually back
into a dunbar number that's much bigger
the mutual followers and the mutual
whatever
could be on the scale of thousands it's
actually about our ability to model
relationships
that's the limit anyway
really fun blog post he says it's only
it's part
one of four or something um some great
work that he's done there so
uh definitely recommend it okay
so that's that's a lot of exposition
about that um
so uh i will say just a few more points
sorry for the walls of the
wall of text that's coming but
we already intuit that relationships are
first class
in the following way anytime you think
about an institution
anything anytime you think about an
organization you
actually are thinking about that
institution not as the building
like the church is more than just a
building with a steeple on it the church
is the relationship of people
acting in a particular way and you think
about this
when there's a vacancy
right relationships are so first class
that when we pop the biological human
out of the relationship
all of those expectations and endpoints
of relationships form a whole
and we call that hole an empty seat or
the office or we're trying to fill
that seat we're still looking we have an
interim chair we're looking for a new
chair
to to formally fill you know to come in
and fill that role
anytime someone talks about roles about
positions
about the office respect the office of
the presidency right
there's there's there is the you can see
it as the whole
and this really cleanly cuts into how we
can analyze
um some of the tribal the dynamics and
the medic war going on around
uh of course right now as we're just
barreling into the election season here
in america
there's a huge number of people who
respect the office they respect the flag
they respect the badge
they respect all of these aesthetics
that we drape around
um the social expectation endpoints the
holes
um and so that is that is a thing that
you know it's it's a thing it's a real
thing
um and to the point about um
yeah so even if you don't have what i
call cartesian self or atomic self
there's nobody sitting in a vacancy
saying i don't think therefore i'm not
right that hole is just there it's
everyone else around them thinking we
need something here and it is not
and the fact that the external
subjective pressure
of of of not selves can go and ideate
and create
the potential for a self that's a thing
right that is actually the reality we
live in
so that has meta i would argue that has
deep metaphysical reality
um and in fact is a much more useful
metaphysical frame than simply viewing
individuals as atoms that go and hey i
would like to interact with you today
it's no today who am i defined by all
these interactions coming in around me
and this gets then to what i alluded to
very early on which is
celebrity and fame culture right if you
go and you read um
she was it wasn't taylor swift she's the
one who thrashes around most widely in
this but
there are a lot of celebrities i feel
like who have now written
books about the crushing pressure of
fame and you don't know what it's like
and all the stuff
and it's real i mean just to to the
great extent possible i empathize with
their plight
because they are dealing with much more
than dumb bar right
they're dealing with like a hundred a
thousand uh uh
ten thousand x dumb bar level of inbound
social pressure on them
to say here's who you are right you're
you're
you're you're like you're this actor
from the show right
hey can i take a selfie with you it's
like no i'm a person i actually have
a self and i have a mother who loves me
who i am and i've got
brothers and sisters i joke with and
like i got all these things
um i have a self that's here and no one
sees you because they see
the boundaries of the avatar that's been
created
and essentially ossified by the medium
of broadcast
the medium of persistent memory of
syndication
right and there's a great story about
how the um
uh the the guy who um the actor who
played the cowardly lion
in the wizard of oz right the original
by the 1950s
wizard of oz the the guy who played the
cowardly line he couldn't get
cast in any more roles because no one
could see him without seeing a cowardly
lion
right and this is every time you hear an
actor talking about well i moved out of
this thing because i didn't want to get
typecast as this
that is that actor saying no i have an
independent self
beyond merely the avatar that's been
created around me
and this is you know the the idea of
celebrity and the idea of fame
is something that well it had existed
organically
back in 1800s but it really is a
production i mean even before that
because you would know the king or you
know well this is the local duke and
this is the blah blah
and there's a rumor mill there's a very
slow organic
rumor mill that is the memetic substrate
for humanity
once we got to the electric age again
back to mcluhan
once you get to a point where the medium
conducts human
uh gossip and rumor mill and
socialization
at light speed you can now direct
and and you have the fidelity of
reproduction
uh whether it's a victorola whether it's
5g or whatever
if you have fidelity production then
what you can do is turn a million
100 million eyeballs all to one
individual
and lock in because of all their social
expectations of that individual
it's they lock in the the social
pressure for that individual to manifest
that avatar
and that individual breaks under that
right it's the
the band that has a one-hit wonder who
goes on stage everywhere and wants to
play any song except their one hit
wonder
right it's it's all of that celebrity
and fame culture
it's deeply uh abnormal i mean relative
to the neocortex relative to
you know for just hunter-gatherers
roaming the savannah
uh just a few hundred thousand years
later it's deeply abnormal we're not
used to dealing with a hundred million
eyeballs looking at us i mean what the f
is that
um so fame and celebrity culture you can
understand the crushing
kind of pressure of that through this
context of you're on the receiving end
of expectations in the social
environment that defines what you are
okay um
uh yeah okay this is just a point about
looking at the relationship looking and
this gets you into that thinking about
the memetic medium
as a first class thing and how that
medium can ossify
reinforce and this is when we talk about
um you know how like we look at
the memes that flow back and forth and
the meme war
um and the tribes and whether it's
humanon or whether it's like trump
being like teflon trump somehow he's
able to like just skirt past everything
um what what you'll notice in this is
that
the the people who are masters at doing
at playing the memetic field
they recognize that the memetic field
has certain dynamics which is that it
takes time
for a meme for a framing for the picture
of a person
to uh both ossify to kind of to just
to persist and then it takes time and
then takes time for it to decay
if you put just enough energy into it
you keep it persisting and so every time
trump goes and calls somebody oh sleepy
joe or like loser blah blah blah
he's basically trying to pop a little
bubble it's like a dolphin blowing an
air bubble like think of trump as a
dolphin
he's blowing a little air air bubble
vortex in a little air bubble ring
and he's putting just enough energy into
it to try to keep that ring going
and and then the person trapped in that
ring is like but i'm not sleepy joe i'm
very energetic here's to me riding a
bike
it's like you're dude you're not even
playing the right game right you don't
need to fight
the ring you need to fight the the the
susceptibility of the medium
that's creating the vortices uh the
vorticity kind of persistent
so anyway all that being said
relationships one more thing to think
about is so to that point about
persistence of the vorticity
um and the social pressures and all
these things uh
what is the metabolism of a relationship
what is the metabolism uh of it in the
sense of like how does it
how does it keep itself alive does are
there relationships
that have um sort of an attractor
to them a tractor dynamic that sucks
energy
or demands energy from their
participants to keep the thing alive
and if it does and it's able to suck
energy in a way that's parasitic or even
detrimental
to not symbiotic but parasitic or
detrimental to the
the the humans the individual's ability
to go into other relationships
we call that a cult right that is almost
by definition what a cult is that's by
definition what a
um you know you see these manipulators
we talk about master manipulators and
con men
that go and completely hack the
psychology of a victim
and what they do when they hack the
psychology is they're creating
a relationship that uh by itself the
victim
the way they relate through that
relationship they kind of get sucked
into it more more
and so it's a you can call it a
vorticity or you call it you know
whatever
an attractor but the point is that um
at that point you know that's one thing
that's
here's an agent so it's an atomic self
using
a particular structured relationship to
uh to capture and parasitize another
agent
but if that relationship starts taking
on a life of its own and starts
parasitizing both of them
to where the manipulator becomes
manipulated
and that does happen right cults take a
life of their own
movements and dynamics take on a life of
their own when we say this thing is
taking on a life of its own
we are again intuitively and in the
vernacular where we have a tool for
talking about this thing
so when those relationships have a
metabolism
well you know what i always do is
whenever i see something with the
tablets i ask does it have agency
doesn't have an agenda what is it
actually trying to do
and most of the time relationships in
these senses they
they um when they emerge in sort of the
human interactions
um that's that's fine that's just like
whatever people hanging out
when the when they have an agenda or a
mission though
they do have agency right that's what we
call an institution or in our
organization
they make it actually the the agenda
explicit we are here our organizational
mission is to do xyz
and if you don't want to sign up for
that and you don't want to be part of
that inter-relationship
then don't be part of that group but if
you are then you should sign up for that
mission right
and this is so anyway this is in the
same sense talking about something very
banal and that everyone has experience
with
but hopefully putting a different lens
on it to how to deconstruct these things
um anyway and then another question is
do relationships have rights
um and i already kind of you know hinted
that we do at least in the legal
framework
we do have concepts certainly if you're
if you're a llc or a c corp
or whatever you absolutely have rights
right there are corporate rights and you
can sue other corporations or
individuals for breach of this and then
the other
we tend to think of those as contract
law not as natural rights but i do mean
this in the sense of
do they have natural rights is there
something when we talk about oh every
person is created equal and all this
like jeffersonian stuff
jefferson didn't really talk about the
relationships you know is there some
jeffersonian view on relationships so
when
two people form a relationship is there
something that we can say there's a
natural
goodness there kind of going back to
last week's thing
is there quality is there metaphysical
weight and quality
in that pattern of interaction and um
is it then therefore immoral to break it
is there something slightly unethical or
moral when we break it or
or or weaken it in some form right some
goes around
um causing children to break their
relationships with their parents causing
um causing lovers to break the
relationships with each other we
intuitively feel like something is lost
when we watch a movie and it's like oh
they you know like they didn't end up
happily ever after
they were going to and then they split
at the end and everyone would say that's
that's kind of sad now we
might go and go meta and say well but it
was better for the individuals because
they can do blah blah
but but no one's gonna deny that there's
a there's a layer of sadness there
because something is lost right so
is there something to talk about at the
metaphysical go back to last week
metaphysically speaking at the social
layer and the cultural layer
when relationships form there when these
standing wave patterns
uh independent of the frogs and their
lily ponds when these standing waves
occur on the surface of the pond do
those waves themselves have a
metaphysical weight
um to them is there some quality they
manifest that we should talk about
as a real thing
anyway that that is the the section on
on um relationships and there's a
section here on
identity as well but i won't get that i
can just stop here and take questions
yes so freaking good man i'm just like
like what's uh yeah maybe we should
pause here to um
take some questions there's a bunch uh
and i love this stuff because like i'll
do that 20 like
1000 different mental models just keep
popping my head like just in relation to
this
and so the first thing that comes to
mind uh i'll double click on the um
kind of parasocial relational aspect and
i'm not necessarily a question to you
it's just like a question that's the
edge of my thinking
um because mcluhan's he started using a
global theater instead of global village
later in his career which is related to
gitabor's idea of the spectacle
uh this concept of parasocial
interactions where someone has a
relationship with
like an actor uh and it's like someone
you know when we
put ourselves on our internet like
people are having a relationship with my
avatar
uh yes with me exactly and then like you
said
um that can be detrimental to someone's
psyche
if everyone starts kind of like
projecting all these things
um but if you can go like meta a little
bit you see that it's just not one
narrative not one intersubjective
narrative being uh projected on you it's
like if you've got all these different
reality tunnels mimetic tribes looking
at you in a different way
um but if you don't have that capacity
to go meta you might miss that that that
kind of
plot line uh but i wrote right here is
like um
type cast at avatar like you know how
you get your you like typecasted your
avatar
is there a way you can be in the
spectacle in the global theater where
you don't get typecasted
uh huh great question um
is there a way to be in the theater
without there's some actors that are
really good like johnny depp
i don't know if johnny that's a good
example but he used to be an example of
this that he didn't get typecasted
because he had such a diverse
uh um talent stack in his acting ability
that he plays so much roles
but then other actors you know they just
get typecasted in a certain way
so is there a way to operate in the
spectacle in the global theater
that avoids this kind of avatar type
casting
ah good okay okay so here's what i say
to that um
is there a difference between being
well we use typecast here in a very um
negative sense
right that it is a binding on my ability
to be my future self or to be whatever
else i want to be
to define myself in some new way
and
if we view it from that lens to say how
do we avoid
being rather than saying typecast which
is the mechanism
let's talk about the harm right is there
a way to prevent myself from being
trapped
in a past incarnation of myself
um because that's what we're really
asking about
um then right am i interpreting the
question correctly how do i prevent
myself from being trapped how do i
retain the freedom to define my future
self
so in the case of actors and whatnot um
they know it's at that point you almost
do have to model
the the the uh broadcast platform
as an agent and say okay hollywood or
the studio execs
because who's doing the typecasting is
the pseudo exec coming to you
saying hey mr depp you're worth you know
you have a net worth of dollar sign x
let me offer you dollar sign x over two
to do this one shitty movie that's
pirates of the caribbean 12
to be the same character again and
you're like god damn it okay
i guess right because that's a lot of
money but the studio exec
is themselves acting as the pointy tip
of the spear
of a lot of social expectation that
basically
just prods you like a cattle prod back
into the same hole you've been in
for pirates of the caribbean one through
eleven right so
so you're you're looking at this and
you're like okay well how to break out
of that
in that case you have to model the
studio exact you have to model the
entire juggernaut of things behind it
as the oppressor as a thing that's
trying to deprive you of your creative
freedom
and i'll give you a very good example of
this um
uh uh chappelle
chappelle has a special on netflix where
he talks about why he noped out
after he had a very successful show and
why he left
and he does this uh he does act i don't
remember which of the netflix specials
it is
i think it's i forget now i'd have to
look it up but maybe we put in the chat
later if i can find it but
he talks about he understood that he was
coming under the pressure of this thing
and he in fact
does it in the way that only dave
chappelle can which is he talks about it
as he relates a story from the
autobiography of a pimp
talking about how much mileage you can
put on a hoe before she breaks and he
felt he was the hoe
and hollywood is putting him putting
mileage on him uh and he basically noped
out before
he ran out of mileage so it's i'm sorry
to turn it really dark and kind of like
gruesome but but that's that is him as a
as an individual saying i am more than
just the boundaries hollywood wants to
put on me
or the studio execs or whatever i'm
gonna do this other thing
how you escape that freedom or sorry how
you escape those shackles in those cases
um some people do it by going to
broadway right you see this all the time
like
uh what's your mother daniel uh
radcliffe right he's like i'm tired of
being harry potter
i'm not a child anymore i'm not a wizard
uh i'm not even a muggle i'm not harry
potter
i'm gonna go do some broadway for a
while right
so he changes to a different medium
broadway does not have the amplification
dynamics
of hollywood right um chappelle was
doing stan
all you see this in comics a lot because
they don't have a ready-made formula
they're making themselves all the time
their job essentially is to transgress
uncomfortably
right that's the best comics they always
they point to truths through
transgression
carlin does this chappelle does this um
so in any case
comics then once they go from this
downstairs like
back at the whatever comedy catch and
they go on to netflix so they go on to
like some big hbo special or comedy
central
boom they blow up and that's when social
pressure comes back in
so so i think you know i don't have a
cute answer for that but how you avoid
the type casting
but i think it is important to realize
that those chains come
from the application medium itself their
result of the medium dynamics
it's like you know a point i made in one
of my blog posts was that
water and ice fundamentally different
things except
it's the same molecule but at different
densities right
and you can take a hammer and smack the
side of like smack it into a pond
nothing happens so some fish kind of
scatter away if you have a big block of
ice you hit
one side with a hammer the other side
can hear the hammer right and our
mimetic medium now our communications
medium are
various things they are now we're all
trapped in ice
uh you know it's much more ringing
there's a lot more ringing going on
um so yeah i don't know that quite
answer that question
i will i'll post a couple more slides
here that from my other
did it work
oh come on oh because i'm in zoom i'm
not actually in keynote
nope i'm okay back in keynote where's
keynote
here's keynote my other window
okay i'm gonna paste some relevant
slides here
this is from my um
can you guys see this
this is from my presentation i did the
the decentralized web
camp uh last uh july in 2019
and this directly ties to digital
privacy
um i've been asking about why do you
want digital privacy since 1993
it always comes down to hiding stuff or
like whatever the government screw the
government they can't
you don't know me um and i articulate
differently
privacy gives us the space to define our
future
selves right free of institutional and
governmental and social
pressures it gives us free reign to be
whoever we want to be it's not a hiding
place it is a womb
and back to this picture you can see
what's my picture here privacy gives
us the ability to have agency within
this realm
and because we all live online now
digital privacy is so important
because i have the right to be myself i
should have the right it's an extension
of jeffersonian natural law for
individual agents
i should have the right to create myself
and to have different kinds of
relationships so when you view the
the right the the the discussion about
oh free speech versus anonymity online
and do the platforms have a blah blah
and
they miss sometimes the fact that the
anonymity is not about
russian trollbots showing up to blow up
democracy the anonymity is to allow
people to explore and be
themselves and in an earlier era before
eternal september like in 1992
when people were online even the very
online people it wasn't dense enough and
they could find niches that
the the it wasn't hot enough in a
mcluhan sense that people could
be anonymous and establish norms build
values you know using these different
ways every usenet group
had these dynamics going on and they
were able to create shared values within
those spaces
this kind of touches on that every
conversation is a space thing but don't
have time to get into that but anyway
this is my point there that digital
privacy and privacy in general as a
concept
should not be about hiding your weed
hiding your porn hiding all your weird
stuff you don't want the government to
know
it should be about letting us develop
our identity letting us develop
peer-wise trust and um letting us build
new inner subjective
uh things it's really about freedom and
and this is i've not heard articulate
like this i'm also not a super deep
expert on the stuff this is kind of what
i came to
um as i was thinking about decentralized
web and why privacy is so important
sorry for the aside there but yeah no no
that's just really good stuff man
um we're at the hour are you cool to
stay
15 more minutes oh yeah absolutely yeah
cool cool
um so if you have any questions start
putting on them if you had any questions
uh that i missed because i wasn't really
following the chats just maybe
paste them uh in the chat box again and
then plus one them as well that would
help me out
i have another question um so you know
you know stoicism
uh their axiomatic principles is live in
accordance with nature
but i kind of like using jordan hall's
uh kind of
not he doesn't talk about stoicism but i
want to repurpose this for like a meta
modern stoicism
is being in in the right relationship
with reality
um and if you're in the right
relationship with reality in the right
relationship with everything right all
these kind of
these these institutions these other
people other relationships
these narratives that exist and then
kind of all the sub personalities
that exist within so it's like
how you described it that kind of a
frame switch of having relationality
first um it's not only descriptively
rich
but it seems to be more ethical
to if we're going to go with the right
relationship with reality
a model that jordan hall was running
with so i was wondering if you can
speak on that the ethical aspect of of
of this
yeah um this touches on some other
mental models too which this is just the
beauty of it it all kind of connects
so jordan is you know he's not wrong but
then it's
the question is like so what are you
really saying jordan you're right i love
jordan i like to be very clear
i have no issue with jordan i love it um
um
but when we talk about you being in
right relationship with reality
that already does this thing um did i
talk about interpolation was it
yes it was talking about interpolation
it's a term from some marxist
scholarship
but interp uh you know maybe i should uh
for those who are not
familiar i should just go ahead and
bring up the um
interpolation share
uh oh yarko's here cool
um yeah so interpolation
this idea that um now this is based
there's a lot of like okay
pretty heavy marxist stuff going on in
here but um
ultimately the idea is that
[Music]
people are defined our identities
our identities are subject to
relationship pressure
to be you know completely honest like
some of this stuff is
is very similar to what i was talking
about right like um
and what their what the marxist critique
was was that the
apparatus of the state or the apparatus
of like the capitalist economic
production sort of uh mentality created
inside people the subjective experience
of i am just a laborer
i am a worker i need work i need a job
right
i'm a consumer i must consume i am i am
a voter
i must go vote it's like no you're a
human being and you get to be whatever
the f you want to be
if you decide that voting isn't for you
anymore you need to go find other human
beings that don't
want to vote and you go do your own
thing right but interpolation is this
idea that
it's it's it's where um okay back to
back to my slide
uh sorry for bouncing back and forth on
the share so much but um
interpolation is what happens
right here at the output port
of that relationship interpolation is
the relationship
maybe the sum integral of all the
relationships of the institutions around
you
telling you what you must be so uh when
to your question about jordan and being
in right relationship
that still unfortunately holds
uh it creates it's an other ring it
creates like a me i'm a me
and i need to be in right relationship
with an other
as opposed to asking what is the me that
is needed to show up
in this relationship so sort of that
sense of like ideas have people
relationships have people and if we view
ourselves
as being um
the union venn diagram of all of the
needs
and all of the the both the gives and
the takes of all these relationships
that we're in
then we can stop viewing ourselves as
simply a little
ball being bounced around how do i be in
residence with this thing that's like
jostling me
all this big nasty reality out there
it's more about
it's sort of stepping into it i don't
know if this there's a
kegan level or whatever else but it's
like stepping a different frame of mind
that says what are all these things
trying what do they want me to be
and what is what is it that i want to be
and you can actually have that question
about how to hold these different
circles
um together um to use the the
the stage analogy right all these
different spotlights
and they're not all the limelights are
not converging where do you want to be
what is the you how do you splash
yourself out like a blob to cover all
those limelights
so that's what i say when you say right
relationship again i don't disagree with
jordan but i would i would delve into it
that way to say let's not
already interpolate ourselves as being
other from reality
but rather see ourselves as co-creating
these relationship fields
because when we're a blob we're not just
a blob spread out trying to cover all
these limelights
being in tension and stress we're a
highly reflective blob
that then reflects light onto other
people we are the limelights putting
pressure on them
i'm demanding my employees to show up in
a certain way i'm demanding my kids and
my wife just show up in certain ways
right
we are so so that's the inter-reflection
and we're all
we're all in the middle of this this
thing anyway
sorry that i don't know if that answered
the question but that that was my yeah i
want to talk to it
that was awesome um so we'll i'm going
to pick a few people and then uh
we'll close out soon um kyle you had
some comments on game b and trust uh if
you can unmute yourself and
share it with the group sure thanks
peter this has been great
um thank you i i
way back in probably 20 minutes into
your talk i
threw out a couple of ideas and
basically just
the thinking is that game b then is
basically
the reinstitutional of trust
um because the game theory of game a
is the deterioration of trust and why
it's self-terminating
right and so how how do you
is is there anything you can talk about
with regard to
restructuring institutions to create
that environment
of trust to change the game theory right
and i know that that's part of the part
of the story that you might be doing
next week but
can you can you give a little riff on
that yeah um
let's see here
okay so what i would say is that uh
let me see here if i can just find this
one part here on the
core of game b
sorry this is just just one second here
um
ah
i think my um my my reasoning is this
trust is um let's see where's my slide
here go back to here
why i said trust is the fundamental is
it this slide something like this
yeah i mean basically you know if if
game a's trust environment is
deteriorating
pretty quickly as we're seeing with all
the social and tech political and
technological forces
that are pushing on it how how do
does it have to break further in order
to re-establish
trust and how do you reshape the
institutions
yeah okay back to that it's got it yeah
okay so here's how i say
um i finally some stuff connected in my
head it just took a second sorry
not enough coffee i've been trying to
have coffee and uh i hear your jerky but
i hear you all good beef jerky yes
absorbs some of the coffee
and you know reduces the coffee
absorption rate in my bloodstream um
so game a as we talk about it you know
if you talk to jordan
uh or maybe daniel schmuckenberger what
not they'll talk about it as being
rivalrous dynamics uh and rivalry and
things like that um
i might talk more about molok uh you
know ginsburg and and
sarcodex style um and and that's that's
my bent on it
which is that we have created
institutions
that um uh
i mean they don't even talk about trust
right they atomize individuals
the whole facility of like the post-war
era now has been creating institutional
political economic systems
memetic systems we ignore the medic
sometimes we talk about this but all of
these different infrastructures of
modernity
atomize the individual they devalue
trust they almost throw trust aside i
mean and the crypto you know the crypto
antics are the worst they're like oh
totally trustless
proof of work blah blah blah right it's
like no we want actually maximal trust
we want to trust preserving
trust is the scarce thing we want to
create infrastructures that promote
inter-human value creation and trust
building
and all of the structures when you view
it and maybe maybe i should just yeah
maybe
next time should be about this a little
bit but but as a preview
all of these infrastructures they create
a way for people to interact without
trust
what is currency at the end of the day
if you go and read sapiens or read like
you know
history of money or whatever else they
ferguson and others like the
money as a currency allows us to
interact without
relating their interactions without
relationship
all right i have a relationship to the
dollar bill i have some hopefully
uh good faith belief in the solvency of
the united states federal reserve
and i'll take a dollar bill for a random
stranger on the street or i'll give him
a dollar bill for a thing
currency calorie shells whatever you
have it currency as a way of
uh providing liquidity for trade allows
um a muslim here and a christian here
and a buddhist over there
2000 miles away to interact with each
other without knowing
without trusting without sharing
anything with each other
so as a scale-out mechanism it is
completely and massively powerful
for that first stage of globalization
but now that we're globally connected by
trade now that we're globally connected
on trustless
interaction the question is how do we
create a global system or create create
a facility that allows
everyone to co-exist on the earth uh
without their memetic tribes being
smushed into each other head long to
conflict
on 9 11 i mean there's a somber date to
be talking about this right
the intersection of cultures and and to
be very clear
i'm a you know full-blown american
through and through nine levels of
tragedy
but if you go and you read what it is
that the fundamentalist will hobbyist
which are funded by the saudis of course
but if you read what the al qaeda
philosophic
and sort of political complaints are
against the encroachment of western
culture and values
into their world the complaint there
doesn't i mean again like just like if
you go and read the unabomber you don't
have to agree with what they did
but it is interesting you know holding a
conflicted mind and reading what is
they're complaining about
and maybe taking a little bit of face
value and what they're complaining about
is
the basically the entire rest of the
world having lost the memetic war to
america because hollywood
right is one of our biggest exports it's
still our biggest export uh to some
extent almost powerful memetic export
so game b back to your question actually
game b is how do we move beyond these
mechanisms
that erode trust atomize individuals get
individuals interacting with each other
within rigid frameworks within
tyrannies of some sort whether it's a
tyranny of trustless interaction which
is
the the uh almighty petro dollar
almighty all fungible petrodollar um or
if it's institutions of hierarchy to say
higher
control and you know you report to your
boss your boss reports their boss
dimension all the way up the chain
you know someone treats you as a
replaceable cog that's
you know whinging about something and
they'll go take care of the grease the
squeaky wheel right
there's all of these structures of game
a are about um
you know dollars and fungible units of
value quote-unquote value for everything
in the world
and then hierarchical scaling and
command and control for all the rest for
the remainder
right for the for the residue that falls
out of that and in fact when we talk
about financialization destroying the
world
it's this well kind of interpolation of
a of a it's the
reduction of everything in the world to
what can be quantified into fungible
units
right even when i was a kid i thought
about it as like i was like you know
i read out millionaires and billionaires
it's so interesting because
the billions and billions of dollars
they hoard and the hundreds of millions
they spend on their art
you can count that in terms of burger
flipping hours of the person flipping
burgers at mcdonald's
right because it's fungible to labor but
it's not fungible because the mona lisa
sitting in a dusty attic somewhere
is not the same as somebody actually
making food for someone else to eat they
need to live
but we live in a world that's required
the sponge ability lens to be imp
impact on everything so anyway
the game b approach is to say can we
solve for sufficiency from the ground up
sufficiency both in terms of sustainable
energy and all of your physical needs
you know all the way up the mazda
hierarchy
but then getting to play where we can
create the sustainable architectures and
infrastructure
so people can build real relationships
with each other it's it's about emerging
conviviality
um bubbles and cells everywhere um
within the cultures and the tribes and
the belief systems and all these inner
subjectivities
anyway long-winded answer but hopefully
that paints a picture
let's uh um end on one more question
um sg you had a question
about multiple cells and some
personalities and whatnot
hey uh yeah thanks hey peter um lots of
great content
i feel like i'll have to listen to the
youtube video a couple times before i
fully digest it
but one question that i've been um
toying with recently is i found myself
realizing that identity is more so
something applied to me than something
that i
necessarily control and one particular
thing that would be useful
is the ability for myself to manage
different identities
for different uses and really treat
identity
as a tool uh rather than a part of
of the self um i'm i'm wondering if you
have any recommendations
how to go about managing that without
losing my head
because it's not something that we've
necessarily evolved to do
um yes you're right it is really a
difficult thing
to manage that and if you mean manage it
from do you mean from like a
psycho social like psycho-emotional
perspective or do you mean it from like
a
technology perspective or all of the
above i think
yeah all the above if you can talk about
it
um i think you know you might find this
interesting this is a you know kind of
the
appendix slides i didn't get to but uh
kalia identity she called herself
identity woman so identitywoman.net
um but she has um a really great
presentation
i have in the link here um you can look
at it you can google for it it's the
domains of identity
um and she talks about it in any context
and um if you look at technology wise
this is much more about distributed and
decentralized identity systems and all
this other stuff but
um but there's many different i think
you mean it more from the social context
right uh sort of like
how do i show up in these different
places um
and i think one of or no do you not mean
that
yeah i think so i do think that they're
quite similar like i do think it reduces
down to decentralized identity
but uh maybe my framing is more on the
social side
yeah well the decentralization of
identity to be clear my interest in it
is about removing power from the
structures that lock things
in not about keeping it always
uh de-atomized right i think people it's
fine to have your identity stored in
some places that place is not
uh like orwellian like you must be this
right so
um to your point about that freedom and
how do we break free of or how do we
fight for our agency against this back
pressure right how do we provide back
pressure to these things
a little bit um i think actually to
start with
seeing the world in this way and trying
to put your uh
build a model of the relationships um
build a model of the relationships and
and hold those in your head
and use those to think about all the
messages coming through them
so um and and to the point of like the
stoic practice when you do reflect on
this
um you know in your daily practice think
about what are the things that upset me
what are the things that got to me maybe
not upset what are things that pleased
me
right because positive reinforcement
dopamine is a really powerful way to
manipulate people too
but you think about what are the strong
signals that came into me today
through what relationships they come in
and
and stop thinking about it as being the
other person
doing it unto me maybe they're trying to
build the relationship in a way so that
the relationship itself
does this to me or holds me in this way
and i can push back
on my end of the relationship and change
it right it's like both of you kind of
pushing
this board and there's a marble bouncing
in the middle and so
think about it in that context so don't
see just
your identity and then the pressures you
feel that's also kind of an
interpolation of a sort because it
casts you as a receiver only you do have
agency in this
um but the way you can manifest that
agency you have to first be very
perceptive you have to think deeply
uh and perceive broadly what is your
emotional state in response to
how that relationship is changing you
and also do
do you think about the relationship as
different than the other person the
person or the things the persons
on the other side of that relationship
um this ties also somewhat to the
gervais theory
uh to uh venkat rouse future base theory
of institutions and organizations
um who can model these relationships
within institutions explicitly
will end up being able to make it to the
leadership tier
those who cannot will not and so anyway
that's my
my feedback to you on that
great um so i think we'll end here
uh that was a lot of fun i really
enjoyed this session
um any any uh closing i'll stop sharing
your screen any closing
um not not particularly just thank you
for for the
you know inviting me to have me here
thanks everyone for sharing your time
it's good to see bruce here yeah bruce i
would love to uh to get your thoughts on
um
uh you know what you think about this
stuff um
but uh yeah just i i i can't actually
see all the participants as i'm talking
here but
um thank you everyone for for joining
and um and just sharing part of your
morning with me
and uh also making some announcements uh
closing answers in the moment but peter
thanks so much again for being a
sensemaker in residence
thank you this is uh quickly becoming
one of my favorite uh series of this
week
um so upcoming sessions uh relatedly to
what we talked about today we have a
collective presencing
um in about 40 minutes uh with rey back
and this is like an intersubjective
meditative practice where we kind of
like get a sense of the contours of
relationality and then real felt sense
level
so that's going to be at the stoa coming
up soon if you want to check that out
good contrast and then tonight we have
socratic social uh with the slow village
raven connolly is going to host this one
uh it used to be called socratic speed
dating but it wasn't
never really about dating so it's uh it
was a little confusing but
it's basically has a speed dating format
where you go in different rooms with
people just get social get to know each
other it's really really fun
that's at 7 p.m eastern time get some
sociality with
the whole stall family and village and
if you'd like
more events you can check out the
website and if you'd like to support us
on patreon you can do so here
that being said thank you again peter oh
yeah one thing um if you could send me
the chat log i'd be happy to
to go and try to you know answer these
things in the discord chat uh to people
sure you can i'll send it to you but you
can save it i think you oh i can't you
just click
the dots and go save chat all right say
chat chat saved
show and finder look at that it just
works cool uh cool
all right thanks everyone see you in
discord and next week right bye
you